What's up everybody, גוט חודש. Gut Chodesh. We are today דף daf
is דף ז. daf zayin. As I said, it's June 7th. Link
to the דף, daf, there you go.
We appreciate the creators of the English calendar. All right, so anyway,
we pick up at the very bottom of ו עמוד ב. vov
amud beis. And for the next three דפים, dapim, two and a
half, three דפים, dapim, we are going to be a little bit
leaving strictly the discussion of נזיקין nezikin and focusing specifically on the
last line of the משנה, Mishnah, which is מיטב meitav and payment
from the best of the land. So what we were introduced first
was a debate of Rabbi Akiva and Rabbi Yishmael when the תורה
Torah says, תורה Torah is talking specifically about שן ורגל, shein v'regel,
at least the way חז"ל Chazal understand it, and it says that
you pay מיטב שדהו ומיטב כרמו. meitav sadeihu u'meitav karmo. You pay
the best. So what does that mean? So the way the גמרא
Gemara is phrased, Rabbi Akiva says מיטב דמזיק meitav d'mazik and Rabbi
Yishmael says מיטב דניזק. meitav d'nizak. The way the גמרא Gemara explained
it is everybody agrees that you're not going to pay more than
you owe, but what is the land that you pay from? People
would much rather have a hundred dollars worth of grade A land
than a hundred dollars worth of grade C land. So therefore Rabbi
Akiva said that's why you pay from your grade A land. Except,
right, that's if you're paying for land, we're going to get to
that today, what happens if you pay in cash or if you
pay in chattel. Okay,
but we're going to get to that. Rabbi Akiva says it is
the best that the מזיק mazik has and Rabbi Yishmael says it
is the best that the ניזק nizak has, you find something comparable
in the land of the מזיק. mazik. If the מזיק mazik does
not have something comparable, he only has something worse or better, then
you get to go then you get an upgrade. Okay, but you
start with the best of the ניזק, nizak, not with the best
of the מזיק. mazik. That's the debate. Now we pick up at
the bottom of ו עמוד ב vov amud beis to unpack the
last line of what Rabbi Akiva said in that ברייתא, braisa, which
was קל וחומר להקדש, kal v'chomer l'hekdesh, okay, and certainly with for
הקדש. hekdesh.
So we pick up the following. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer,
it is six lines from the bottom, seven lines from the bottom
on ו עמוד ב. vov amud beis. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva
omer, Rabbi Akiva says, לא בא הכתוב אלא לגבות לנזיקין מן העידית.
lo ba kasuv ela ligvos l'nezikin min ha'iddit.
The תורה Torah is only coming to tell you when it says
מיטב meitav that when you're coming to collect from נזיקין, nezikin,
and I'm going to get to that in a minute, but you
know but actually no, let me get to that right now, which
is there's all types of damages, even though the תורה Torah is
talking about שן shein and רגל, regel, you might remember that we
said a day or two ago, כולם כאבות לשלם ממיטב, kulam k'avos
l'shaleim mi'meitav, okay, תחת נתינה ישלם כסף. tachas nisinah yishaleim kasef. All
right,
we have this big גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah and we learn now
first of all from שן shein and רגל regel to the other
ארבעה אבות נזיקין arba'ah avos nezikin that all of them pay with
מיטב, meitav, and then from keywords תחת נתינה ישלם כסף, tachas nisinah
yishaleim kasef, we learn out that any type of collection of damages,
whether it's גנב gannav or גזלן gazlan or a שומר shomer or
any of these you know big categories that we the ארבעה אבות
arba'ah avos about שבת, sheves, ריפוי, ripuy, בושת, boshes, all types of
damages are ממיטב. mi'meitav. Okay,
so what Rabbi Akiva says is לא בא הכתוב אלא לגבות לנזיקין
מן העידית, lo ba kasuv ela ligvos l'nezikin min ha'iddit, all type
of collection of damages is going to be from the best, and
now the line that we're going to focus on for a little
bit, וקל וחומר להקדש, v'kal v'chomer l'hekdesh, and certainly when it comes
to הקדש. hekdesh. If it's true about a lay person, it's certainly
true about הקדש. hekdesh. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי קל וחומר
להקדש, mai kal v'chomer l'hekdesh, what does that mean? אילימא דנגח תורא
דידן לתורא דהקדש, ileima d'nagach tora didan l'tora d'hekdesh,
we owe הקדש hekdesh money. So if when we owe a lay
person money, he collects damages from מיטב, meitav, when we owe הקדש
hekdesh damages, הקדש hekdesh will collect from us from מיטב. meitav. So
what would be the case we would owe הקדש hekdesh damages? One
of our oxen gores a הקדש hekdesh ox. Okay, the גמרא Gemara
says what do you mean מיטב? meitav? You don't pay anything in
that case. שור רעהו אמר רחמנא ולא שור הקדש. shorei rei'ehu amar
rachmana v'lo shorei hekdesh. It says if one ox gores the ox
of your neighbor's ox, your neighbor's ox and not הקדש's hekdesh ox.
Your neighbor means a lay person like yourself. So if your ox
gores הקדש's hekdesh ox you don't pay. Now let me just you
don't pay anything. Now I'm just going to pause for a second,
it says fine, that's about an ox goring an ox, but there's
Rabbi Akiva said, you know, לשלם לנזיקין מן העידית, l'shaleim l'nezikin min
ha'iddit, there's a lot of other damages, right, if I burn הקדש's
hekdesh field, let's say I don't know, you know, let's come up
with some other cases, a הקדש hekdesh ox falls into my well,
you know, any of the types of נזיקין. nezikin. Why do why
do so fine, שור shor you're exempt. So תוספות Tosafos basically says,
he quotes ירושלמי Yerushalmi and he says from this גמרא Gemara it's
clear, from the ירושלמי Yerushalmi it's clear that somehow we learn out
from the case of שור shor and there's also a similar פסוק
pasuk by בור bor and then we and whatever and then we
apply it to אדם adam and through a certain series of steps
we basically say that this is true about all damages. All damages,
if you damage הקדש's hekdesh property, you are exempt from payment. Now
he does say that if you're an אדם המזיק adam hamazik and
you do it intentionally, at least rabbinically you'll have to pay. If
you burn down their field, right, that's not even אש, esh, that's
like כוחו, kocho, that's ידיים, yadayim, I mean we'll talk about that
when we get to אש, esh, okay, you tear up their you
know you steal their money, you whatever, okay, he says but okay
well stealing also might be a little bit different. Anyway, but basically
תוספות Tosafos says from this גמרא Gemara it's clear from other גמרות
Gemaras that this is not limited to goring oxen. You are technically
exempt in all cases of damages of הקדש's hekdesh property, which is
like... Shocking, right? You'd think קל וחומר, kal vachomer, right? All right,
so the גמרא Gemara says, but if that's true, then you're never
going to be collecting, הקדש Hekdesh is never going to be collecting
מן העידית. min ha'idit.
So, אלא, ella, so here would be the case, the גמרא Gemara
says. ואומר הרי עלי מנה לבדק הבית. Ve'omer harei alai mane libedek
habayis. So you owe money, it's not the real case of thank
you, it's not a real case of damages, you owe money. You
say you obligate yourself to give a hundred dollars to the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. ואתא גזבר ושקל מעידית. Va'ata gizbar veshakal me'idit. So
the גזבר gizbar would come and he would collect and he'd collect
from the עידית idit best of your land if you didn't pay
cash. So the גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute, that shouldn't be
true, לא יהא אלא בעל חוב, lo yehe ela ba'al chov, then
you're just a normal, you know, debtor. It's not damages, it's a
debt. ובעל חוב בבינונית. Uva'al chov bevenonis. And הקדש Hekdesh is the
creditor, בעל חוב ba'al chov means the creditor. הקדש Hekdesh is the
creditor, and the creditor is only entitled to collect from בינונית. benonis.
Now, you might have said maybe הקדש Hekdesh is better, but Rabbi
Akiva said קל וחומר להקדש. kal vachomer lehekdesh. He said whatever is
true by הדיוט hedyot is certainly true by הקדש. hekdesh. He didn't
say הקדש hekdesh was better, he said הקדש hekdesh was at least
as good, was as good, okay? So, and anyway, this might follow
the principle before like we said earlier also that we don't want
to assume that things don't work within our normal system unless we're
normally forced to. Okay? So it can't be you owe הקדש hekdesh
money, that would be בינונית. benonis. It can't be damages, you're never
liable damages for הקדש. hekdesh. So what's the case? So the גמרא
Gemara says, top of ז עמוד א, zayin amud alef, וכי תימא
סבר רבי עקיבא כו בעל חוב נמי בעידית. vechi teima savar Rabi
Akiva ko ba'al chov nami be'idit. Oh, well maybe it's still that
you just owe them money but maybe he holds that even for
a lay person if you owe somebody money you give the and
they're collecting land, they collect the best land. And therefore he's saying
if that's true about a lay person it's true about הקדש. hekdesh.
So the גמרא Gemara says, no, איכא למיפרך. ikka lemifrach. You can't
even make that קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Because since we've already established
that a you don't owe damages to הקדש, hekdesh, so there goes
any קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Clearly your sense of liability to הקדש
hekdesh is less. So you're not you can't make even a קל
וחומר kal vachomer even if it was true that you'd have to
pay a lay person a debt you'd have to pay them the
עידית, idit, you could not prove the best quality, you could not
prove that that would be true by הקדש. hekdesh. איכא למיפרך, Ikka
lemifrach, מה לבעל חוב שכן יפה כוחו בנזיקין. ma leba'al chov sheken
yafe kocho benezikin. Okay, when you're paying a lay person a debt,
maybe you would pay them with the best because they have all
this power when it comes to נזיקין damages that you owe them
money and you pay the best. תאמר בהקדש, Tomar behekdesh, how am
I entitled to assume it's the same type of payment to הקדש
hekdesh for a debt? שהורע כוחו בנזיקין. Shehoru kocho benezikin. הקדש Hekdesh
is very disadvantaged when it comes to נזיקין, damages, they don't collect
anything. Okay, so now that we've established we have two big questions
here: number one is you're never paying הקדש hekdesh damages, and number
two is goodbye any קל וחומר kal vachomer because הקדש hekdesh is
really a weaker when it comes to these issues. So what the
heck is Rabbi Akiva talking about? So the גמרא Gemara says, לעולם
דנגח תורא דידן לתורא דהקדש. le'olam denagach torda didan letorda dehekdesh. Fine,
back to what we said before. Our ox gores הקדש'ס hekdesh's ox.
ודקקשיא לך שור רעהו אמר רחמנא, Vedekakashya lach shore re'eihu amar rachmana,
your neighbor's ox, שור רעהו, shore re'eihu, רחמנא, rachmana, ולא שור הקדש,
velo shore hekdesh, and not a הקדש'ס hekdesh's ox. רבי עקיבא סבר
לה כרבי שמעון בן מנסיא, Rabi Akiva savar lah keraf Shimon ben
Menasya, he doesn't read the פסוק pasuk that way. He holds like
רבי שמעון בן מנסיא Shimon ben Menasya דתניא, detanya, רבי שמעון בן
מנסיא אומר, Rabi Shimon ben Menasya omer, רבי שמעון בן מנסיא Shimon
ben Menasya says, שור של הקדש שנגח שור של הדיוט פטור. shore
shel hekdesh shenagach shore shel hedyot patur. If if their ox gored
our ox, הקדש hekdesh is exempt, הקדש hekdesh has immunity from any
damages, okay. שור של הדיוט שנגח שור של הקדש, shore shel hedyot
shenagach shore shel hekdesh, if our ox gores their ox, so in
that case בין תם בין מועד משלם נזק שלם. bein tam bein
mu'ad meshalem nezek shalem. Not only are we liable, but we have
to pay נזק שלם, full damages, okay. And this is the way
רבי שמעון בן מנסיא Rabi Shimon ben Menasya reads this: כי יגח
שור איש את שור רעהו, ki yigach shor ish et shor re'eihu,
right? שור איש, shor ish, שור רעהו, shore re'eihu, ומכרו את השור
החי וחצו את כספו. umachru et hashor hachai vechatzu et kaspo. When
it's your neighbor's ox you pay half, okay. When it's however הקדש'ס
hekdesh's ox, okay הקדש hekdesh is not שור איש shor ish and
it's not שור רעהו, shore re'eihu, right? So the פסוק pasuk is
talking about when a lay person's ox gores a lay person's ox,
שור איש את שור רעהו, shor ish et shore re'eihu, you pay
half. If it's הקדש'ס hekdesh's ox, it's not half. What is it?
If a הקדש hekdesh ox does the goring, it's zero. If however
if it's our ox goring הקדש'ס hekdesh's ox, it's also not half.
What is it? Full. Okay so, actually reading it in a way
which makes sense from a position that you want to of course
you know give advantage הקדש hekdesh within these laws. So that's going
to guide us to read that yes, when הקדש'ס hekdesh's ox is
involved it is not the standard
law. If הקדש hekdesh is the gorer, fully exempt. If הקדש hekdesh
is the goree, then we're fully liable even the first three times.
So therefore once you say that, you say that you're liable when
you do damages to הקדש. hekdesh. And you certainly have a קל
וחומר kal vachomer because you're even liable in some cases of a
goring ox you're liable even more. So now according to רבי שמעון
בן מנסיא, Rabi Shimon ben Menasya, if you're going to pay best
עידית idit when you're when you owe damages to a lay person,
you're certainly going to pay עידית idit when you owe damages to
הקדש. hekdesh. Oh wait one minute, okay, now אי הכי i hachi
says גמרא, Gemara, if that's true, רבי ישמעאל ורבי עקיבא מאי בעידית
דניזק ובדינו דנזיק פליגי? Rabi Yishmael veRabi Akiva mimai de'idit denizak vedibino
denezik paligi?
If רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva is introducing this idea that you owe
damages to הקדש hekdesh and that you pay the best, why are
we so certain that the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva and
רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael is about whether you figure out best based
on the damage... of the damagee. דילמא דכולי עלמא בדניזק שיימינן? dilma
d’kulei alma bidneizak shamman? Let’s
suggest a completely different read of the whole debate. Maybe everybody agrees
you pay based on the damagee, okay? והכא ve-hacha בפלוגתא דרבי שמעון
בן מנסיא ורבנן קמיפלגי? be-phlugta de-Rabbi Shimon ben Manashia ve-rabanan kamiphilgi? Maybe
they're really debating about something completely different. They're not debating about the
quality of land that you pay. Maybe they're debating about whether you
owe money to הקדש Hekdesh when you damage הקדש, Hekdesh, okay? There's
the issue of רבי שמעון בן מנסיא. Rabbi Shimon ben Manashia. So
of course it doesn't read at all in the language, which is
what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. אי הכי ee hachi says...
where'd I skip a line... אלא רבי עקיבא סבר כרבי שמעון בן
מנסיא. ella Rabbi Akiva savar ke-Rabbi Shimon ben Manashia. רבי עקיבא's Rabbi
Akiva big חידוש chiddush is that you pay damages to הקדש, Hekdesh,
ורבי ישמעאל סבר כרבנן. ve-Rabbi Yishmael savar ke-rabanan. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
says
no. But maybe they're not debating at all the quality of the
land you pay with. So it's a bizarre question. Clearly that's not
true. The גמרא Gemara says no, אם כן מאי לאו בא הכתוב?
im kein mai lav ba ha-katuv? What is it when רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says the פסוק pasuk is coming to tell you that
you pay מיטב? meitav? קל וחומר להקדש kal va-chomer le-Hekdesh was the
second statement. Clearly רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva first point is to emphasize
that you pay from the best quality land of the מזיק. mazik.
Clearly the הקדש Hekdesh thing is an afterthought, is a second point.
ועוד מאי קל וחומר להקדש, ve-od mai kal va-chomer le-Hekdesh, which is
the same type of point. It's קל וחומר להקדש kal va-chomer le-Hekdesh
means that's a second point that I'm making, right? But my basic
issue that I'm focusing on and debating with רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
is what is the nature of the payment. All right. ועוד אמר
רב אשי תניא בהדיא ve-od amar Rav Ashi tanyia be-hedya anyway. רב
אשי Rav Ashi says he has an explicit ברייתא: braita: מיטב שדהו
ומיטב כרמו ישלם מיטב שדהו של ניזק ומיטב כרמו של ניזק דברי
רבי ישמעאל רבי עקיבא אומר מיטב שדהו של מזיק ומיטב כרמו של
מזיק. meitav sadehu u-meitav karmo yeshaleim meitav sadehu shel neizak u-meitav karmo
shel neizak divrei Rabbi Yishmael Rabbi Akiva omer meitav sadehu shel mazik
u-meitav karmo shel mazik.
It goes by the מזיק mazik not the ניזק. neizak. So the
reason the גמרא Gemara pushed it a little bit is if you
go back to the ברייתא braita we did yesterday and look, רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva never said מיטב שדהו של מזיק. meitav sadehu shel
mazik. He says לאו בא הכתוב אלא לגבות מן
העידית, lav ba ha-katuv ella lighbot min ha-idit, which is like, okay,
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael also says מן העידית. min ha-idit. It's just
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said the עידית idit of the ניזק. neizak.
What did you add, רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? So that's why the
גמרא Gemara was exploring a little bit. Maybe he's not really arguing
on how you define עידית. idit. Maybe his whole חידוש chiddush was
the second part of his statement. But the גמרא Gemara says no,
it sounds like he has a first point to be making before
he gets to הקדש. Hekdesh. And the ברייתא braita says explicitly that
the first point that רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva making irrespective of the
הקדש Hekdesh question is that you figure it based on the מזיק
mazik not the ניזק. neizak. So הקדש Hekdesh is a second discussion
but the major debate is מזיק mazik versus ניזק. neizak. And in
addition says the גמרא רבי עקיבא Gemara Rabbi Akiva actually holds that
you have to pay הקדש Hekdesh for damages and you're going to
pay them the same way you would pay the הדיוט. hedyot. Now
there are questions. I'll do them in the order I saw the
hands. Charlie.
This is an unusual
ordering of the rabbis. רבי שמעון בן מנסיא Rabbi Shimon ben Manashia
is actually after רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
Right, of
course, well רב אשי Rav Ashi after everyone. But anyway, רב אשי
Rav Ashi is just teaching a ברייתא, braita, he's not teaching his
own thing. But yeah, the גמרא's Gemara saying that when רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva holds like רבי שמעון בן מנסיא Rabbi Shimon ben Manashia
doesn't mean he's following רבי שמעון בן מנסיא, Rabbi Shimon ben Manashia,
he means he's anticipating רבי שמעון בן מנסיא. Rabbi Shimon ben Manashia.
It's just an articulation of an idea that we say has to
be what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is assuming, which is really true.
It sounds like that. If רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva saying קל וחומר
kal va-chomer you pay הקדש Hekdesh damages, so presumably he's saying you
can be paying הקדש Hekdesh damages. Now by the way, it's also
possible that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say sort of against the
point that תוספות Tosafot is making. He might agree that when it
comes to goring oxen you don't pay. He just might think that
all other damages you do pay. The גמרא's Gemara making an assumption
that if you don't pay by goring oxen you don't pay by
הקדש Hekdesh at all. Right. Barko, yes.
Does he still agree that you'd still collect the קנס knas of
ניזק neizak for הקדש, Hekdesh, right?
Yes, that's a different issue but that's not a payment issue. Yeah.
רבי Rabbi Yoel.
Would you say that רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva opinion is more close
to a קנס knas than...
in other words... No, why? Because if you pay according to עידית
idit the מזיק, mazik, it's not what he damaged.
You also didn't damage the עידית idit of the ניזק. neizak. You're
not paying more than you owe. You're just giving him a payment
of something that is easily, you know, that can be easily liquidated,
that can easily be...
Doesn't it take a bigger bite? Doesn't it think it's more injurious
to the מזיק mazik for him to have to pay out?
Might be, but look at the ניזק. neizak. The ניזק neizak lost
his property, so why shouldn't you give him something that's easily convertible
rather than something that's harder to convert? I mean I do agree
that it is being harsher than a normal, that's the חידוש. chiddush.
Look, the פשט pshat of the פסוקים pesukim is that in a
particular case, which okay חז"ל Chazal read it as שן ורגל shen
ve-regel but a lot of פשטנים pashtanim say that it basically means
a willful intentional burning down of somebody's field, it sounds like in
a particular case you're going to get a heavy burden of מיטב
שדהו. meitav sadehu. What the גמרא Gemara does is it can say,
first of all that's not a heavy case, it's a normal שן
ורגל, shen ve-regel, second of all it's true about everything. So when
it's true about everything you can't read it as a קנס, knas,
but it also therefore reads that you're not going to pay more
than you owe. מיטב שדהו meitav sadehu does not mean if you
destroy one bad acre you pay one good acre. It's just the
type of property you collect from. So the גמרא Gemara sort of
turns down the volume on everything. It universalizes it that it's all
types of payments of נזק, nezek, but it also means that it's
not more than you owe. Now the fact that you have to...
If you give from high quality, okay, you know, the guy's entitled
to something that's more easy to convert than something that's harder to
convert. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* certainly does not see this as
a קנס *knas* by the way because it universalizes it. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. It says רמי ליה אביי Abaye
לרבא *Rami leh Abaye le-Rava*, אביי Abaye *Abaye* challenged רבא Rava *Rava*.
כתיב *K'tiv*, meaning רמי *Rami* actually means more specifically, he showed a,
he threw two contradictory texts together. Okay, so here's what he did.
He said, כתיב *K'tiv*, one פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* says מיטב שדהו meitav
sadeihu, ומיטב כרמו ישלם *Meitav sadehu u-meitav karmo yeshalem*. מיטב meitav. אין
מידי אחרינא לא *Meitav in, midei achrina lo*, only the best. ואתניא
*V'atanya*, but a ברייתא braita. *baraita* teaches ישיב *Yeshiv*. It says כסף
ישיב לבעליו *kesef yeshiv l'ba'alav* by the case where an ox falls
into a well. Money he shall return to the owner and you
keep the carcass. Okay, and the ברייתא braita. *baraita* teaches what does
that mean return money to the owner? לרבות שווה כסף *L'rabot shava
kesef*, anything of equivalent value. Remember קידושין *kiddushin*, שווה כסף ככסף *shava
kesef k'kesef*. Anything that has value, doesn't even have to be cash,
can be popcorn, can be paperclips. Okay, ואפילו סובין subin? *v'afillu subin*,
even like
סובין subin *subin* bran. Okay, so you can pay him in pennies
and paperclips or whatever, it doesn't have to be מיטב Meitav *meitav*.
So how do you reconcile this? I am going to exactly, I'm
going to ruin the surprise. We're going to spend the whole דף
*daf* figuring it out, but since we mentioned it before and since
it really seems somewhat a pretty transparent answer, or maybe it's only
transparent once you know the answer. Anyway, is the difference whether it's
land or it's not land. Land has to be the best. Land
is hard to convert, it's hard to sell, you want to really
wait till you get the right price and so on. And chattel
is seen as relatively easy to convert and therefore any type of
chattel, even if it's not cash, even if it's paperclips, that's okay.
So if you want to pay in immovable objects, you can pay
in anything. If you want to pay in land, you have to
pay from the best. Actually, an interesting story, I was going to
check it out but I forgot. But I remember hearing many many
years ago, the people remember those old fogies here, people remember the
shopping channel? Maybe they still have that, I don't know, do they
still have the shopping channel? Anyway, you know that they get on
and they like just hawk like random crazy items. Apparently it got
started because there was this one company that some other company was
going out, owed them like I don't know ten thousand dollars, but
they were like basically declaring bankruptcy and going out of business. So
they just paid them with their with their like inventory and they
paid them with I don't know forget what it was, like you
know like blenders or something like that. They actually did this and
they were like what are we going to do with ten thousand,
hundred thousand dollars worth of blenders? So they basically like you know
did something like took a TV slot and basically auctioned it all
off. And then they realized, hey we can make money doing this.
So that's how the shopping channel got started apparently. Anyway, so just
to show you that you can actually if you if you maybe
if you have access to mass media, right in a little town
I'm not sure that that works. But anyway, but you can convert
chattel easier, more easily than you can convert than you can convert
land. What?
You can't take it with you. The chattel if you don't find
local buyers.
Oh, that's also a good point. Right, you can also move it
somewhere else, right. Right, so it's not just that the price is
hard, it's harder to get you know the right price, but it's
exactly that. You can always you can always it's restricted to who
who's going to buy it as opposed to. Of course there are
shipping costs and there's you know labor costs in terms of getting
it to the next town that's going to buy it, but right.
But anyway, that's the assumption that chattel is we're not as מקפיד
*makpid* that it be of a certain quality because of because of
those issues. Yes, Charlie.
The חז"ל *Chazal* may have stumbled onto an eternal truth that high
quality property is easy to sell and low quality property can't be
sold for any price. Compare real estate in Seattle versus Detroit.
Very. Yeah, exactly, you know, when it's in a bad location then
it's never going to get. Okay, so good. So now let's now
that we know the answer let's figure out how we're going to
get there. Because אביי Abaye *Abaye* doesn't know the answer right away.
So אביי Abaye *Abaye* says like this. לא קשיא *Lo kashya*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to have a few other answers
before it gets to this one. That's not difficult. כאן מדעתו כאן
בעל כרחו *Kan mida'ato kan b'al karcho*. So the first thing the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says is that the difference is are you is
the property being seized or are you basically paying of your own
of your own volition? If you pay up of your own volition,
anything I choose to pay you have to take. Whereas if you
had to get a court order to come and seize my property
and I made you go to court and get the court and
I sort of you know imposed that burden on you then you're
entitled to take whatever you can find, you know, it's up to
you and you can take the best. You're entitled to take the
best. Okay, so that's a reasonable distinction. המה *Amar* so the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this. כאן מדעתו כאן בעל כרחו *Kan mida'ato
kan b'al karcho*. אמר עולא בריה דרב עילאי *Amar Ulla b'rei d'Rav
Ilai*, דיקא נמי *deika nami*, oh maybe that even can be read
into a close read of the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*. דכתיב *D'chtiv*, because
the verse says ישלם
*yeshalem* as opposed to ישיב *yeshiv*, ישיב *yeshiv* to return suggests it's
on your own initiative. So if it's on your own initiative you
can give anything. But ישלם *yeshalem* can be read as shall pay,
like shall be made to pay. So that's when it has to
be the best quality, when it's בעל כרחו *b'al karcho*. אמר ליה
Amar lei, אביי *Amar leh Abaye*, so אביי *Abaye* resisted this answer.
מי כתיב יושלם *Mi ktiv yushalam*? Shall be shall be paid up,
right, which means against your will. ישלם כתיב *Yeshalem ktiv*. He will
pay. מדעתו *Mida'ato*. Or maybe ישלם also means on your own initiative
you'll pay up. So I'm not sure I can read that into
the פסוק. pasuk Now, of course, just because you can't read it
into the פסוק, it's not so מדויק, meduyak, doesn't mean it's a
wrong answer. It's still a reasonable answer. But אביי is not happy.
אביי is going to look... אביי wants a different answer. So אלא
אמר אביי, Ela amar Abaye, כדמר. kidmar. No, maybe here's the way
to resolve, to explain what is the difference between when you get
the best and when you can pay the... and when you can
even do the worst. Like what the
master רבה Rabbah teaches, דתניא, detanya, we taught a ברייתא. הרי שהיו
לו בתים שדות וכרמים, Harei shehayu lo batim sadot ucheramim, somebody had
a lot of land, a lot of property, houses and fields and
vineyards. ואינו מוצא למכרן, Ve'eino motzei lemochran, and he is not able
to sell them, right? It's a bad market. He would have to
sell them at a significant loss. Now what's the case? This is
in the context of מעשר עני. ma'aser ani. You only give מעשר
עני, ma'aser ani, right, the מעשר ma'aser you give on the third
and sixth year to somebody who's an עני. ani. Okay, what constitutes
an עני? ani? An עני ani is somebody who has less than
two hundred זוז, zuz, now like the value of a כתובה. ketubah.
Okay, now,
I'm sorry, not only מעשר עני, ma'aser ani, it's also לקט שכחה
ופאה, leket shikcha upeah, all of the gifts to the poor and
מעשר עני. ma'aser ani. Now, what if somebody has, you know, net
worth is two hundred זוז, zuz, but he has zero liquid assets?
It's all, you know, it's all sort of invested in real estate
or whatever and if he would have to liquidate any of it,
right, he would have to take a very serious loss. Is that
person entitled to collect מעשר עני? ma'aser ani? Now there's two ways
of thinking about this and two very different ways of reading the
text in front of us. I'm going to read it רש"י's Rashi
way, but I'll just tell you the...
asset rich and cash
poor, asset rich and cash poor, thank you very much, that's the
right language for that. Okay, so there's two very different ways of
reading this text and I'm going to tell you or maybe תוספות
Tosafot has even a third and fourth way. I'm going to tell
you the two major ways and then we're going to focus on
one of them. One way of reading this text is I am
doing... going to give you מעשר עני ma'aser ani as a רחמנות
rachmanus to you to hold you over until you can sell the
stuff at a better, you know, at a better... at a reasonable,
what do you call, price. Okay, so really the reason I'm giving
it to you is not so much because you're an עני ani
and you're entitled for it, like you might have, I don't know,
a thousand זוז zuz worth of property there, but it's just to
save you from a significant financial loss. Like you right now have
to, you know, you need cash, you can't, you know, you would
have to... so it's an interesting idea that I could give you
מעשר עני ma'aser ani to save you... it counts as מעשר עני
ma'aser ani because you're... because you're cash poor, right? Even though you're
really not poor at all, but it's to save you from a
significant financial loss. Okay, that's one way of reading this. רש"י, Rashi,
that's תוספות's Tosafot way or a way that רש"י Rashi reads it
and then he sort of rejects it. The way that רש"י Rashi
prefers to read it and the way we're going to read it
is no, no, no, the question is just whether I consider your
net worth to be two hundred זוז zuz based on current financial
realities. The fact that you would lose money because you needed cash,
that doesn't make you a poor person to be entitled to מעשר
עני. ma'aser ani. But here's the question: you have property worth two
hundred זוז. zuz. But in today's financial climate, given the current realities
right now, you would only be able to sell it for a
hundred זוז. zuz. If you would like wait out the tide, right,
you know, wait a couple of months or whatever, you'd be able
to get two hundred זוז. zuz. But right now, it's only worth
a hundred זוז. zuz. Are you now rich or poor? Are you
entitled to collect מעשר עני? ma'aser ani? You see the difference? The
difference is not "I'm giving it to you to save you from
a financial loss," it's "do I assess your net worth based on
how much the property generally is worth or how much you would
be able to get... how much you would get for it right
now?" Okay, so that's the way רש"י Rashi is going to read
it and that's the way we're going to read it. Right.
So this is the kind of the question... my whole... my whole
difficulty with the unit or degree of measurement. Like what does that
mean that it's ultimately worth two hundred זוז? zuz?
Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to ask. Well, that's
what... well, let's see because that's essentially... I understand what you mean,
it's generally worth, you know, markets are always changing.
Right, exactly. So that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara is going to
ask. Okay, so let's take...
you achieve a financial calculation, do you know?
You look at your money in the bank... Okay, so let's take
a look at what the גמרא Gemara says. הרי שהיו לו בתים
שדות וכרמים ואינו מוצא למכרן Harei shehayu lo batim sadot ucheramim ve'eino
motzei lemochran
and you cannot sell them at the normal market price. מאכילו אותו
מעשר עני עד מחצה. Ma'achilo oso ma'aser ani ad mechtzah. You give
him מעשר עני ma'aser ani until half. Again, the way רש"י Rashi
reads that, it means that... that
you are willing to basically... oh, let me just double-check רש"י Rashi
that I'm getting this right.
Right, so רש"י Rashi says like this, we are willing to, if
there is basically, here's also part of the point, it's sort of
like what Charlie was saying before about Denver. Let's say there's a...
No market price for it. Nobody's interested in buying it. How much
do we assess its current value to determine if you're an עני
ani or an עשיר, ashir, if there's no market for it right
now? So what the answer is is עד מחצה. ad mechtza. We
assess its value at half the normal rate when there is a
market for it. Again, how do I know what the normal rate—how
we know what the normal rate is is a good question. But
assuming this property normally goes for $100 an
acre, the farm land in Kansas normally goes for $100 an acre,
but right now we're in a terrible financial downturn and nobody is
buying any land. How much do we assess your net worth to
determine if you have 100 זוז zuz or 200 זוז zuz based
on your land? And the answer is עד מחצה. ad mechtza. If
there's no market for it and we can't assess a price value,
we will determine its value at half of what we determine is
the normal rate, and then we will determine if at assigning it
at half, you have 200 זוז, zuz, then you don't get מעשר
עני. ma'aser ani. If under half you have less than 200 זוז,
zuz, we can still give you מעשר עני. ma'aser ani. Okay, clear
to everybody?
Yeah, we've seen this in the כתובה, ketubah, right? Yeah, yeah. So
here we have an interesting situation where someone who is receiving מעשר
עני ma'aser ani
is חייב chayav in לקט leket and פאה peah to other poor
people.
That's an interesting question. That could be true also if you have
less than 200 זוז. zuz. Okay, anyway, so that's the point.
Okay, so the whole comparison to מעשר עני ma'aser ani is different
than נזיקין Nezikin in that in נזיקין—the Nezikin מעשר עני, ma'aser ani,
we have an arbitrary amount, right? It seemed to me that the
200 זוז zuz must represent something like the purchasing power for, you
know, to keep you for, right, for like
the
year, like a year's salary is essentially what 200 זוז zuz is,
but
a year's
expense, right, but
it's arbitrary and also changeable much like
עני. ani.
Right, so in a second, you'll see the comparison is not going
to be a direct—right, you're right. The comparison is not going to
be direct, it's really just to borrow the scenario that רבא Rava
uses to explain this ברייתא. So let's hold off and see what
the גמרא Gemara, does with this. Okay, but anyway, that's the way
רש״י Rashi reads it. We have to figure out how much your
net worth is when nobody is willing to buy any of the
property, so we assess it at half of its normal value.
מחלין אותו עד מחצה. machilin oto ad mechtza. והוי במר, ve'havi be'mar,
and the master asked: היכי דמי? heichi dami? Now רש״י Rashi says
עד מחצה ad mechtza means—he also explains this—let's say therefore your property
was normally would go for 200. Now we assess it at 100.
How much מעשר עני ma'aser ani can we give you? So here's
a question. Normally, right, if if if—I mean there's actually a story
like this in a גמרא Gemara. that somebody had 199 זוז, zuz,
okay? So at that type of a person, if he bumps into
you and says please give me מעשר עני, ma'aser ani, you can
give him 1000 זוז zuz worth of מעשר עני ma'aser ani because
at the moment you give it to him, right, he only has,
you know, he's an עני. ani. But if you first give him
one זוז zuz of מעשר עני, ma'aser ani, he can't go to
the next guy and get any more because now he's no longer
an עני. ani. All right, so there's a whole story in the
גמרא Gemara about that, like somebody basically lent him a דינר dinar
and whatever ruined his opportunity—anyway, whatever. So so
what the way רש״י Rashi reads this is, your value now went
down to 100 because there's no market for your $200 worth of
land, your 200 זוז zuz worth of land. I can give you
up to $100 of מעשר עני, ma'aser ani, but not more. So
let's see what the—what's going to bother the גמרא Gemara with this.
גמרא Gemara says like this: היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case?
והוי במר, ve'havi be'mar, the master רבא Rava asked: היכי דמי, heichi
dami, what's the case? אי דזל ארעא דכולי עלמא, ei d'zal arsa
d'kuli alma,
if everybody's land has depreciated ודידי נמי זל בהדייהו, u'didi nami zal
bahadeihu, including yours, אפילו טובא נמי ליתי
ליה—give afilu tuva nami lisi lei him more than 100, meaning right
now he only has—his net worth is 100, he's an עני, ani,
so in one, in one gift, you can give him as much
as you want. Why are you only giving him up to 100?
Right now he's an עני, ani, give him as much as you
want, at least as one gift. Okay, ליתי ליה, lisi lei, דהזול
דכולי עלמא
נמי—everybody's de'hazul d'kuli alma nami land is less, so that's his status.
His status is an unequivocal עני ani and therefore he should be
able to get as much as you want to give him in
one gift. אלא דאוקיר ארעא דכולי
עלמא—everything ela d'okir arsa d'kuli alma else's land is of a high
value, ודידי—and u'didi
his is of a low value. Why would that be that his
is of a lesser value than it normally is? איידי דאייעל ונפיק
אזוזי זל
ארעא—because ayidi d'ayeil ve'nafik a'zuzei zal arsa he is desperate for money.
That's the phrase of the גמרא, Gemara he's going in and out
for money. If he's desperate for money, people can buy his land
at a bargain. Okay, so everybody else can wait it out and
they'll, you know, they'll get their price if they, you know, give
it the normal three months it takes to get your price, but
this guy is desperate for money, people know he's desperate for money,
and therefore he's going to have to sell at a loss. And
therefore the question is, you know, is he really an עני? ani?
You know, technically he does have $200 of assets, 200 זוז zuz
of assets, it's just that he's desperate so he's going to get—he's
going to get taken advantage of a little bit. But that doesn't
stop him from being an עני. ani. I mean, that doesn't mean
that he doesn't have $200 of assets. Technically he's still rich. Of
course, you would think in that case you'd have more רחמנות rachmanus
on him, help tide him over. Okay, but anyway, this is the
way רש״י Rashi is reading it. reading the גמרא. Gemara So if
that's true, if everybody's land including his is really worth the normal
price and really worth two hundred זוז, zuz, just because he's desperate
right now does not change his status and make him into an
עני. ani. אפילו פורתא נמי לא ליתבו ליה. Afilla purta nami lo
lisvu lei. He shouldn't give him anything. He has two hundred זוז
zuz worth of assets. The fact that he has to sell it
for less because he's desperate does not change the fact that objectively
speaking he has two hundred זוז zuz worth of assets. Does that
make sense?
Meaning, so
everyone,
everyone's land is at the normal value and his, he has to
sell it at a loss because he's desperate for money. It goes
below worth? No, and because of that it goes under two hundred,
but the גמרא Gemara. says, but that shouldn't entitle it to be
considered under two hundred. Just because he's desperate does not mean that
objectively his assets are worth less than two hundred. Objectively his assets
are worth two hundred. If he weren't desperate, he would get two
hundred dollars for it. So the fact that his particular circumstances make
him desperate does not mean that objectively he has less assets, his
assets are worth less. Okay?
It's estimated by an independent appraiser at least two hundred but practically
would not be worth.
Exactly. And right. An appraiser comes and says it's worth two hundred,
but he needs the money desperately by tomorrow and he's going to
have to sell it at a fifty percent reduction, you know, just
to get it off his hands within the next day. That doesn't
mean that he doesn't have two hundred זוז. zuz. That just means
he's desperate and he's going to sell stuff for less than it's
worth.
So if you read the last line in עמוד א׳ amud aleph
with a question mark, right? וזלא? Vezala?
Already? No, no, no. וזלא, Vezala, because he is desperate his land
is worth less, but if that's true, if he's going to get
less just because he's desperate, that doesn't mean that objectively it's worth
less. ואפילו פורתא נמי לא ליתבו ליה. Ve-afilla purta nami lo lisvu
lei. Right, his land really isn't
worth less, right, he's just going to sell it for less than
it's worth. Right, it's subjective versus objective reality.
Yeah, exactly, exactly.
And everyone found
out he needs money, so they're lowballing.
Right, exactly. Okay.
Which does not mean that objectively his assets are worth less. It
just means that he's going to get taken advantage of right now.
So okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, so what's the case? If
he genuinely is an עני, ani, if objectively everybody's land is worth
this amount of money and objectively he's an עני, ani, then you
can give him as much as you want in one gift. It
shouldn't be limited. If objectively he's an עשיר, ashir, just because his
particular circumstances mean he's going to have to take a loss, then
he's still an עשיר ashir and he shouldn't be entitled to anything.
So the גמרא Gemara says, ואמר מר עלה, Ve-amar mar ala, and
the master Rabba explained it the following way. לא צריכא, Lo tzricha,
you need it for the following case. דביומי ניסן יקרא ארעא וביומי
תשרי זול ארעא. Debyomei Nissan yakra ara ubyomei Tishrei zal ara.
During the spring, that's when the land is going at a premium
because all the farmers they want to buy their land in the
spring in order to have time to get ready to do the
planting and preparing. That's like the proper, that's the best time to
take possession of the land in order to plan for the next
agricultural cycle. But if you buy it in the fall, in the
fall it's like, you know, you're too late to get everything in
place for this year. You need it to be preparing your land
and planting it or whatever. So if somebody, if you're buying land
in the fall, that's when it's not ideal for the farmers to
own the land and therefore you're going to buy, its value is
much less. Okay?
דכולי עלמא, Dekulei alma, so normal people who want to sell land,
נטרי עד ניסן. natri ad Nissan. You wait until Nissan, you wait
until the spring to sell it at a premium. Right now? Right,
right, for like real estate, residential real estate in the spring. Actually,
I got to read you this great תוספות. Tosafot. Look at תוספות.
Tosafot. דביומי ניסן יקרא ארעא. Debyomei Nissan yakra ara. תוספות Tosafot says,
ואם תאמר התינח שדות כדפירש הקונטרס לפי שיחרוש בקיץ ויזרע במרחשון. Ve-im
tomar hateinach sadot kedefeirash hakunteres lefi sheyachrosh bakayitz veyizra bemarcheshvan. Right, so
of course the fields you want to buy in the spring because
you're going to plow in the summer and plant in the fall.
So you have to buy the field, right, that's true. You have
to buy the field in the spring. You buy them in the
fall and it's too late. Okay. אלא בתים, Ela batim, but if
it's houses, because remember it said בתים שדות וכרמים, batim sadot ucheramim,
it also mentioned houses. בתים מאי חילוק יש בין ניסן לתשרי? Batim
mai chiluk yesh bein Nissan le-Tishrei? What difference does it make? ויש
לומר שרגילים ליקר בזמן שרגילים לשכור בתים ולאחר ששכרו זול. Veyesh lomar
sheragilim leyaker bizman sheragilim liskor batim vel-achar she-shachru zal. Yeah, because there's
a seasonal market.
Right? Seasonal market. Houses go up presumably also maybe, you know, if
that's when the season sort of change and you know, and that's
when like you're planning for the next year. You know, it's sort
of like I think, right, I don't job, a lot of that
happened like around the September time people switched jobs, whatever, because it's
also linked to the school year. No? Is that why?
Depends on people. Some people go like after March when they get
their bonuses.
Oh, I see. Whatever. Okay. Anyway. Whatever it is. Okay. So there's
also a seasonal market for houses. So normal people, if you have
the luxury, you wait until the market is at its height and
then you sell. והאי הואיל ואצטריכו ליה זוזי, Vehai ho'il ve-itztreichu lei
zuzei, since he needs cash, זבין כדהשתא. zavin kedehashta.
He's going to have to sell based on the current market value.
Now, that means though, it's not just because he's desperate people are
taking advantage of him, which makes it totally subjective. This is the
value right now. but normal people don't sell at this time of
year, but at this time of year, it's only worth a hundred
dollars an acre, not two hundred dollars an acre. That's the objective
value right now but normal people would wait till it got worth
till it was worth more. Okay? So והכא נמי אשרוהו Vehacha nami
ashrohu ואיצטריכא ליה זוזי ve'itztareicha lei zuzi זבין כדהשתא zavin kedehashta he's
tell he'll sell he'll have to sell at the current value. עד
פלגא Ad palga until half, you know, if you have to lose
take a loss of go, you know, lose fifty percent of what
you would have gotten if you had sold it in ניסן. Nissan.
אורחיה למיזל, Orchei lemizal, then you that's the normal amount that it's
to depreciate between ניסן Nissan and תשרי. Tishrei. טפי, Tfei, more than
half, לאו אורחיה למיזל lav orchei lemizal is not the normal amount
to depreciate. Okay, so that's how he describes the scenario and therefore,
how does it explain this case? You're a guy, you have land
worth two hundred זוז, zuz, but right now it's תשרי. Tishrei. You're
cash-poor. How much is your land worth? So what we will say
is, we will assess your land we cannot assess it at less
than half its value. Because anything less is not considered a a
normal value for that land, right? If it's worth two hundred in
ניסן, Nissan, then we don't we're not prepared to assume it's worth
less than a hundred in תשרי, Tishrei, but we will go as
far down as a hundred. And therefore, if by reassessing its value
based on תשרי Tishrei prices, you're an עני, ani, then you're entitled
to take מעשר עני. Maaser Ani. Okay, so that's how we explain
that case over there. Now רש"י's Rashi still a little bit bothered.
Fine, but once you're an עני, ani, you can give the guy
give the guy as much as you want in one gift, like
we discussed before. Once a guy's an עני, ani, you can give
him as much as you want in one gift. So רש"י Rashi
says well, you're sort of an עני ani and you're sort of
not. Right? Since in three months from now, whatever, you know, since
by ניסן Nissan you're not going to be an עני, ani, you're
only an עני ani in today's prices, but in tomorrow's prices you're
not going to be an עני, ani, you're in this like middle
category where we'll give you מעשר עני Maaser Ani but not more
than will go take you over the level of two hundred. We'll
give you מעשר עני Maaser Ani to bring your net worth up
to two hundred. Okay, so that's the basic case there. Everybody got
it? Alright, so if you're if your
subjective realities of being desperate and being taken advantage of don't matter,
but the reality that right now at today's prices it's low, but
for normal people if you said to a normal person how much
is this person's assets worth, you would assess it based on ניסן's
Nissan prices. You know, for you, we have to assess it based
on תשרי's Tishrei prices. So that sort of makes you an עני
ani right now even though in some other through a different lens
you're not an עני. ani. And therefore you're entitled to מעשר עני
Maaser Ani but up to a certain limit. Alright, that's פשט. pshat.
Now what does that have anything to do with us? Okay, well
it allows us to introduce this idea of land that changes value
from one time of year to a different time of year. And
now we're going to try to use that to explain whether we
say עידית iddit and when we don't say עידית. iddit. So let's
take a look. That was a fascinating digression. Okay, and now let's
take a look. So הגמרא Hagmarah says like this. Now. I'm... sorry.
I'm... sorry. We're doing...
sorry. So that means like like technically, no one would do this,
but technically every third and sixth year, you put your land on
the market in תשרי Tishrei and you're you're eligible or they do
an audit.
No, you don't have to sell it, you audit it. You have
an audit. Okay, yeah. Now, הגמרא Hagmarah says like this. והכא נמי
גבי נזיקין, Vehacha nami gabei nezikin, here by נזיקין, nezikin, we would
say the same thing. דינא בעידית. Dina be'iddit. The normal rule is
עידית. iddit. דאמר ליה איהו. De'amar lei ihu.
Now, but let's say the ניזק nizak says הב לי בינונית טפי
פורתא. hav li beinonit tfei purta. You know what?
I would prefer rather than taking one acre of עידית, iddit, I
would prefer taking an acre and a half of בינונית, beinonit, which
is the same value. Okay, because that's the whole point, it's worth
less per acre. I want a little more בינונית beinonit rather than
in terms of the amount of land, but the same value. All
right, he he is actually asking for the option for בינונית. beinonit.
Okay, so for whatever reason, he he doesn't why you know, he
it neighbors his land, he's got some idea that he doesn't want
עידית, iddit, he wants
בינונית. beinonit. דאמר ליה איהו הב לי בינונית טפי פורתא. De'amar lei
ihu hav li beinonit tfei purta. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so the
מזיק mazik can say to him, listen buddy, אי שקלת כדינך שקול.
ei shaklat kedinach shakul.
If you take like, you know, if you want to take, take
like the law says. You take עידית, iddit, you don't get to
choose. The תורה Torah says עידית, iddit, you get עידית. iddit. It's
funny, the מזיק mazik wants him to take עידית. iddit. כדהשתא, Kedehashta,
and based on its current market's value. ואי לא, Ve'i lo, if
you want me to give you an option of doing בינונית, beinonit,
then I will tell you, fine, you want בינונית? beinonit? Be my
guest. בשוקא כיוקרא דלקמיה. Beshuka kiyokra delakamei. But we're going to assess
it based on the highest the the higher seasonal rate, the ניסן
Nissan rate. Okay, ניסן Nissan market.
So that's when we're basically saying does he get עידית iddit or
does he get בינונית? beinonit? We're basically saying it's a bizarre read.
It's like you can get עידית iddit or you can get אפילו
סובין. afilu subin. But אפילו סובין afilu subin is now not actually
now you know so to say like why is it סובין? Subin?
It's בינונית. beinonit. Oh it's סובין subin because I get to dump
it off on you and I get to give it to you
at the higher market rate. So that's the אפילו סובין. afilu subin.
But it seems very crazy. Like why do you get to like
so הגמרא's hagmarah going to say really? מתקיף לה רב אחא בר
יעקב Matkif lah Rav Acha bar Yaakov אם כן הורעת כחן של
ניזקין אצל בינונית וזיבורית. im kein horat kochan shel nizakin etzel beinonit
veziburit. You're telling me... that you're worse off if you collect from
the lower property land? רחמנא אמר ממיטב. Rachmana amar m'meitav. The תורה
Torah is trying to give an advantage to the to the person
that's damaged, and says he gets to collect from the best land.
That אמרת מבינונית וזיבורית נמי לא, amarta mi-beinonis ve-ziboris nami lo, and
you're telling him you're not entitled to collect from grade B and
C. And if you want to collect from grade B and C,
you have to do it at a loss, you have to do
it based on a higher market rate. That's crazy! Why should that
be the הלכה? halacha? אלא אמר רב אבא בר יעקב: ella amar
Rav Abba bar Yaakov: אי איכא לדמויי לבעל חוב מדמינן לה. i
ika lidmuye le-bal chov midaminan la. If you want to sort of
make a comparison, let's sort of talk about what would be let's
think about the case of a creditor, of a בעל חוב. bal
chov. בעל חוב דיניה בבינונית. Bal chov dina be-beinonis. A בעל חוב
bal chov is normally as we said entitled to collect grade B
land. ואי אמר ליה הב לי זיבורית טפי פורתא, Vee amar lei
hav li ziboris t'fei porsan, now let's say he says to the
debtor, you know what, I'd rather collect grade C land but a
more, an acre and a half of grade C land. אמר ליה,
the creditor can say the debtor can say to him: אי שקלת
כדינך שקלת כדהשתא. ee shakalt k'dinakh shakalt k'de-hashta. If you want what
you're entitled to grade B, take it current market rate. ואי לא,
Vee lo, and if you want me to do you a favor
and give you grade C land, שקלת כיקרא דלקמיה. shakalt k'ikra de-lekamei.
Fine, I'll give you grade C land but based on the higher
market rate. So, so it's the same question though, like, you know,
why should he be entitled meaning this case of רבה Rabba of
higher and lower market rates isn't relevant to our case of נזיקין.
nezikin. Our case of נזיקין, nezikin, clearly the ניזק nizak is given
an advantage, right, מיטב שדהו, meitav sadeh-hu and therefore he should not
be disadvantaged by going down a level. But what he seems to
say is but maybe by בעל חוב, bal chov, since the פסוק
is not coming out and saying that you have this strong advantage,
it's just a reality, you get grade B.
Here's the difference in what he's saying is, by the case of
ניזק, nizak, the idea that you get the best is explicitly labeled
as an advantage. We're giving you an advantage to get grade A.
Therefore you should never get disadvantaged if you want to choose to
move down to B or C to be forced to take based
on different market rates. But he said, if you want to think
sometimes that might play out, maybe it plays out by בעל חוב.
bal chov. Because by בעל חוב, bal chov, the fact that he
gets grade B is just the law. It's not saying there's an
advantage, that's just the way it is, you get grade B. So
maybe if you want anything other than the law, if you want
grade C, then maybe, you know, he's entitled to say fine we'll
use the higher market rate. Do you hear the difference? One case
it's framed as an advantage, so you can't be disadvantaged by changing
it. Here it's not framed as an advantage, so here maybe the
guy would say you want grade C, be my guest, but we'll
do higher market rate. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't like that either.
גמרא Gemara says מתקיף לה רב אחא בריה דרב איקא: matkif la
Rav Avacha brei de-Rav Ika: אם כן, im ken, נעילת דלת לפני
לווין. na'alta delet lifnei lovin.
This is terrible
policy because nobody would lend money because I'll say I never want
to not have my cash on me. Why? דאמר ליה, De-amar lei,
because the creditor can say: אי הוו לי זוזי, ee havu li
zuzei, if I had never lent you the money and I had
the cash on me right now, הוי שקילנא כדהשתא, havi shakolti de-hashta,
I could have bought your grade C property based on current market
rates. השתא דזוזי גבך, Hashta de-zuzei gabakh, now that I lent you
money and I'm trying to just get my money paid back and
I want to take your grade C property which I could have
bought at current market rates, אשקול כיקרא דלקמיה, eshkol k'ikra de-lekamei, I
have to buy it market rates that is going to be later?
So who's gonna ever want to lend money?
Obviously, it's saying is it would make no sense to apply this
idea that you can force somebody who's going down a level to
take it at future market rate. Of course, the obvious next option
is fine, it makes no sense if they want to go down
a level. But what if they want to go up a level?
Then maybe you're entitled to say use later market rates. Let's read
the next גמרא. אלא אמר רב אחא בריה דרב איקא: ella amar
Rav Avacha brei de-Rav Ika: אי איכא לדמויי לכתובת אשה מדמינן לה.
i ika lidmuye le-kesuvas isha midaminan.
Now again, this is not to explain our case about נזיקין nezikin
and מיטב. Meitav, We're still just talking about when can we use
this model of lower and higher market rates, current and future, in
some other
הלכה. halacha. Not in our case of נזק, nezek, but in the
following case: in a woman coming to collect her כתובה. kesuvah. Because
a woman coming to collect her כתובה kesuvah is clearly disadvantaged. She
collects from grade C. She in terms of what land she collects
from, it's not grade A, it's not grade B, she collects from
grade C. דכתובת אשה דינה בזיבורית. de-kesuvas isha dinah be-ziboris. She collects
from grade C. ואי אמרה ליה איהי, Vee amar lei eehi, and
now she said to her husband: הב לי בינונית בציר פורתא, hav
li beinonis batzer portan, I'd rather collect grade B less of grade
B, a half of acre of grade B as opposed to a
full acre of grade C. אמר לה, Amar lah, then she's asking
actually for something more than she's entitled to. In that case, when
you're not asking to make it easy, when you're not going down
a level, you're going up a level, אמר לה, amar lah, he
could say to her, listen: הני אי שקלת כדינך שקלת כדהשתא. hanei
ee shakalt k'dinakh shakalt k'de-hashta. If you want to take my land,
then you'll take what the law is, you'll take grade C based
on current
market rate. and not today's market rates. That's when you can use
this idea of ניסן ותשרי Nissan and Tishrei market rates if somebody
is asking for an accommodation. They basically, or not an accommodation, it's
not the right word, but some type of a, you know, of
a favor essentially. They want to go to more than a higher
quality than they're entitled to. תוספות Tosafot says you could have also
said it in the בעל חוב Bal Chov scenario. The בעל חוב
Bal Chov says I don't want grade B, I prefer to have
grade A and less of grade A. So in that case, the
debtor's entitled to say: fine, I'll give you grade A. I can't
just give it an arbitrary huge value, that would be of course,
you know, extortion,
but what I can do is I can say you want grade
A, we're going to use ניסן's Nissan market rates and not today's
market rate. Okay, so that's pretty fascinating that if somebody wants a
certain type of an upgrade, you can sort of choose as the
debtor, you know, you can say I'll give it to you but
I'm going to insist on using a high, you know, the high
seasonal rates rather than the low seasonal rates. All right, anyway, that's
in terms of applying ניסן ותשרי. Nissan and Tishrei. But we still
have to go back and answer our question. Is it מיטב Meitav.
or is it סובין? The best or is it bran? Okay, so
the גמרא's back to that. אמר רבא. Amar Rava. Okay, so the
גמרא says like this: מכל מקום קשיא, Mi'kol makom kashya, okay, we're
still back to square one, what's the answer to our question? Is
it the best or is it bran? Okay, so again, the first
answer the גמרא rejected, which was quite a nice answer, whether it
was given willingly or whether it was being seized, but אביי rejected
that. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא's going to give an
answer. כל דיהבלי, Kol d'yavlei, and this is not going to be
the final answer. כל דיהבלי ממיטב ליתבי
ליה. Kol d'yavlei mi-Meitav lay-sav-lei. No, ah, yes you can give bran,
but you have to give your best bran. Okay, yes you can
give paper clips, but you have to give the best paper clips.
Okay? So it has to be מיטב, Meitav. but it could be
anything. Okay, but of that genre that you're giving, it has to
be the best. So the גמרא says: ומיטב שדהו כתיב. V'Meitav sadeihu
kesiv. That's not true, it says best land. Okay, there's no idea
of the best bran, the best paper clips. It's not true. אלא
כי אתא רב פפא ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע מבי רב, Ella
ki ata Rav Pappa v'Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua mi-bei Rav, when
they came from the house of רב, Rav, פירשוה, perushuha, this is
going to be the final resolution. כל מילי מיטב הוא. Kol mili
Meitav hu. Any type when it comes to chattel, anything is considered
מיטב. Meitav It's not a contradiction. Chattel is always מיטב. Okay? דאי
לא מזדבן הכא, De-ilo mizban hacha, like Joe was saying before, if
you can't sell it here, מזדבן במתא אחריתי, mizdabin b'masa achrisi, you
just transport it to another town. You will always find a market.
There might be costs associated with finding a market, but anyway, you'll
always find a market. So the idea of giving of insisting on
a higher quality does not make so much sense on chattel. לבר
מארעא, L'bar mi-ara, the one thing that we would not say this
is is land. דלית ליה, D'leis lei, because there you can only
there's only a small number of people that you can sell it
to. And therefore, it really, you know, if somebody gets low quality
land, they might be it might be able to, you know, completely
unusable. So if you have to pay back for damages, you have
to give them something that really they could be able to convert
and to sell. Okay? דלית ליה ממיטב, D'leis lei mi-Meitav, there you
have to give him of the high quality. כי היכי דליקפצו עלה
זבינא, Keichi d'likfot alei zavina, in order that purchasers will jump at
the opportunity. Okay, so therefore, that's why מיטב is only by land,
anything that's chattel does not have to be cash, can really be
in any type of property. There's an interesting discussion that תוספות Tosafot
has in a number of places about what is the story by
a loan. Okay, that's when there's a debt that's incurred because of
some act or damages or whatever. If I borrowed a hundred dollars
in cash from you, can I give you back a hundred dollars
in paper clips? Because you can say: yeah, go sell it somewhere.
What do you mean go sell it somewhere? I gave you a
hundred dollars in cash, I'm entitled to a hundred dollars back. Okay,
in cash. So that's basically the position that תוספות Tosafot takes, that
when it comes to a loan, actually you gave cash, you're entitled
to cash back. The person cannot give you מטלטלין metaltelin and say
go find somebody to sell it. Okay, this idea by the way,
excuse me, this idea that you can give even סובין by chattel
is in case of a debt that is incurred through damages or
similar types of things, but not when you took money. If you
took cash, you have to pay back cash. Yes.
Is this also a discussion by פועל? poel?
Yes, by
that's a good point, right, by תוספות Tosafot has that discussion too,
right, by salary. I'm not remembering how תוספות Tosafot comes out about
that. But right, that would be another good point where it's like
contracted as opposed to giving
them in pottery that they then have to go sell.
Right, right, right.
But what if it's not con what if it's not contracted?
Well, okay, what's the fallback position? What's the Well, no, no, obviously
if it's written explicitly in the contract, but I meant that it's
a relationship that was an agreed-upon, right Right, that's a good question.
I forget what תוספות Tosafot says about that, I'd have to check
and get back to you on that.
Yeah. Do בתי דינים Batei Dinim follow this today with allowing people
to pay
I don't know what בתי דינים Batei Dinim do today. All right,
let's take a look. By let's get started on the next topic.
בעי מיניה רב שמואל בר אבא מעוקבא. Ba'ei minei Rav Shmuel bar
Abba mi-Akva. מעקרוניא מרבי אבא. me'Akrunya me'Rabbi Abba. So רב שמואל בר
אבא Rav Shmuel bar Abba from this place asked רבי אבא, Rabbi
Abba, כשהן שמין בשלהן שמין או בשל עולם שמין? K'shehen shamin, beshelahen
shamin o beshel olam shamin? When they assess its value, when they
say it's the best. Best, is that a subjective or is that
an objective determination? Right, if there's grade A land, but there's triple
A land, okay, and the מזיק Mazik has A and triple A,
so if you do you do by the objective definition of best,
so that would be A, or do you do by the מזיק's
Mazik definition of best, which would be triple A? Okay, you can't
say the opposite, the opposite you could say let's say he has
grade B, because then of course he's going to give B, he
can't give more than he has. You understand? So the way to
raise the question subjective or objective, or the scenario would be that
he has better than what the rest of the world considers to
be grade A. If he has worse, only worse, then of course
he's not going to give grade A, he doesn't have grade A
to give. But let's say he has better than what the world
considers to be grade A. Would he give the world's grade A
or would he give his best? Alright. כשהן שמין, K'shehen shamin, when
they assess the value, בשלהן שמין, beshelahen shamin, based on his property,
או בשל עולם שמין, o beshel olam shamin, or based on some
objective standard? אליבא דרבי ישמעאל לא תיבעי לך. Aliba d'Rabbi Yishmael lo
tiba'ei lach. According to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael there's no question, דאמר
בדינזק שמינן. d'amar b'dinizaq shaminnan.
He says it's what the it's the ניזק, nizaq, so obviously you
look at the ניזק's nizaq best. It's מיטב שדהו of the ניזק,
nizaq, right? כי תיבעי לך אליבא דרבי עקיבא דאמר בדמזיק שמינן. Ki
tiba'ei lach, aliba d'Rabbi Akiva d'amar b'demaziq shaminnan. The question is רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that says the מזיק. Mazik. מאי? Mai? מיטב שדהו
אמר רחמנא למעוטי דניזק. Meitav sadeh-hu amar rachmana l'ma'utei d'nizaq. When it
says "his best", it means as opposed to the ניזק. nizaq. If
the ניזק nizaq only has bad quality, you pay the general grade
A, you don't pay whatever is the ניזק's nizaq best land is.
או דילמא, O dilma, or we say, but it would only be
the universal grade A. או דילמא O dilma no, למעוטי דעלמא נמי.
l'ma'utei d'alma nami.
It's excluding even the universal grade A. It's you, the מזיק. Mazik.
We identify your prime real estate. You know, your Fifth Avenue Manhattan
real estate, and that's what you have to pay. That is way
catastrophically higher than the world's grade A. Okay, but that's what
we would determine. מאי? Mai? מיטב שדהו אמר רחמנא או דילמא למעוטי
נמי? Meitav sadeh-hu amar rachmana o dilma l'ma'utei nami? אמר ליה
רחמנא אמר מיטב שדהו. Amar lei: rachmana amar meitav sadeh-hu. It says
"his best field". ואת אמרת בשל עולם שמין? V'at amart b'shel olam
shamin? And you want to say it's some universal standard? How more
explicit can you get? It says "his best field". So his best
field means his best field. Okay, we will continue with this tomorrow
to see how we come out.